Several years ago here at TED, Peter Skillman
قبل عدة سنوات، هنا في تيد، قدّم بيتر سكيلمان
introduced a design challenge
منافسة تصميم
called the marshmallow challenge.
تسمى منافسة حلوى المارش مالو.
And the idea's pretty simple:
والفكرة غاية في البساطة.
Teams of four have to build the tallest free-standing structure
فريق مكوّن من اربعة يجب أن يبني أطول هيكل مستقيم
out of 20 sticks of spaghetti,
من 20 قطعة من الماكرونة،
one yard of tape, one yard of string
وشريط بطول ياردة واحدة، وحبل بطول ياردة
and a marshmallow.
وحلوى المارش مالو.
The marshmallow has to be on top.
يجب أن تكون المارش مالو على القمة.
And, though it seems really simple, it's actually pretty hard
ورغماً عن أنها تبدو بسيطة للغاية، إلا انها صعبة للغاية،
because it forces people
لأنها تجبر الناس
to collaborate very quickly.
على التعاون بسرعة جداً.
And so, I thought this was an interesting idea,
لذا فقد فكرت بأن هذه فكرة مثيرة،
and I incorporated it into a design workshop.
وقمت بتضمينها في ورشة عمل للتصميم.
And it was a huge success.
وقد كان نجاحاً باهراً.
And since then, I've conducted
ومنذ ذلك الحين، قمت بعقد
about 70 design workshops across the world
حوالي 70 ورشة عمل للتصميم عبر العالم
with students and designers and architects,
مع الطلاب والمصممين والمهندسين المعماريين،
even the CTOs of the Fortune 50,
وحتى مع مدراء التقنية لأكبر خمسين شركة،
and there's something about this exercise
وهي شئ متعلق بهذا التمرين
that reveals very deep lessons
الذي يكشف عن درس بالغ العمق
about the nature of collaboration,
حول طبيعة التعاون،
and I'd like to share some of them with you.
وأرغب في تقاسم بعض منها معكم.
So, normally, most people begin
إذاً، في العادة، يبدأ معظم الناس
by orienting themselves to the task.
بتوجيه أنفسهم لهذه المهمة.
They talk about it, they figure out what it's going to look like,
يتحدثون عنها، ويتعرفون على كيف سيكون شكلها،
they jockey for power.
ويتنافسون على الفوز،
Then they spend some time planning, organizing,
ثم يقضون بعض الوقت في التخطيط، والتنظيم.
they sketch and they lay out spaghetti.
إنهم يرسمون ويخططون المكرونة
They spend the majority of their time
ويقضون معظم وقتهم
assembling the sticks into ever-growing structures.
في تجميع العصى في الهياكل المتنامية
And then finally, just as they're running out of time,
ثم أخيراً، ينفذ الوقت منهم،
someone takes out the marshmallow,
يأخذ شخص ما حلوى المارش مالو،
and then they gingerly put it on top,
ثم يضعها بحذر شديد على القمة،
and then they stand back, and -- ta-da! --
ثم يتراجعون إلى الوراء، و " تاداا"!
they admire their work.
ويثمنون عملهم.
But what really happens, most of the time,
لكن حقيقة ما يحدث، في معظم الأوقات،
is that the "ta-da" turns into an "uh-oh,"
هو أن تلك ال "تاداا" تتحول إلى " أو-هو،"
because the weight of the marshmallow causes the entire structure
لأن وزن حلوى المارش مالو تتسبب في إلتواء
to buckle and to collapse.
الهيكل وإنهياره.
So there are a number of people
لذا فهناك عدد من الناس
who have a lot more "uh-oh" moments than others,
الذين لديهم لحظات "أو-هو" أكثر من البقية،
and among the worst are recent graduates of business school.
ومن بينهم الخريجيين الجُدد من كلية إدارة الأعمال.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
They lie, they cheat, they get distracted
إنهم يكذبون، يغشون، وينصرف إنتباههم،
and they produce really lame structures.
وينتجون هياكل عرجاء حقاً.
And of course there are teams
وبالطبع هناك فرق
that have a lot more "ta-da" structures,
التي لديها لحظات هياكل "تاداا"،
and among the best are recent graduates of kindergarten.
والأفضل ضمنهم، هم الخريجون الجُدد من رياض الأطفال.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And it's pretty amazing.
وهذا شئ رائع حقاً.
As Peter tells us,
كما يخبرنا بيتر،
not only do they produce the tallest structures,
لا يقومون فقط بإنتاج أطول الهياكل،
but they're the most interesting structures of them all.
لكنها أيضاً أكثر الهياكل إثارة بين الجميع.
So the question you want to ask is:
إذاً فالسؤال الذي ترغب بطرحه هو:
How come? Why? What is it about them?
كيف؟ لماذا؟ وماذا عنهم؟
And Peter likes to say that
ويريد بيتر منا أن نقول أنه،
none of the kids spend any time
" ليس من بين الأطفال من يقضي أي وقت
trying to be CEO of Spaghetti, Inc. Right?
في محاولة أن يصبح مديراً تنفيذياً لشركة ماكرونة." صحيح.
They don't spend time jockeying for power.
ولا يقضون وقتاً في محاولة التنافس على السلطة.
But there's another reason as well.
لكن هناك سبب آخر أيضاً.
And the reason is that business students are trained
والسبب هو أن طلاب إدارة الأعمال متدربون
to find the single right plan, right?
على إيجاد طريق واحد صحيح، حسناً.
And then they execute on it.
ثم يقومون بتطبيقها على الهيكل.
And then what happens is, when they put the marshmallow on the top,
ما يحدث بعد ذلك، عندما يضعون حلوى المارش مالو على القمة،
they run out of time and what happens?
ينفذ وقتهم، وماذا يحدث؟
It's a crisis.
إنها أزمة.
Sound familiar? Right.
تبدو مألوفاً؟ أليس كذلك.
What kindergarteners do differently
وما يفعله تلاميذ رياض الأطفال بطريقة مختلفة،
is that they start with the marshmallow,
هو أنهم يبدأون بحلوى المارش مالو،
and they build prototypes, successive prototypes,
ويقومون ببناء نماذج متتالية،
always keeping the marshmallow on top,
ودائماً يبقون على المارش مالو على القمة،
so they have multiple times to fix when they build prototypes along the way.
لذا فلديهم عدة مرات لإصلاح النموذج المبني بإعتلال طوال الطريق.
Designers recognize this type of collaboration
لذا فالمصممون يعرفون هذا النوع من التعاون
as the essence of the iterative process.
كعملية تكرار جوهرية.
And with each version, kids get instant feedback
ومع كل نموذج، يتلقى الأطفال ردود أفعال فورية
about what works and what doesn't work.
حول عملهم وما لم يعملوه.
So the capacity to play in prototype is really essential,
إذاً فالمقدرة على اللعب في النموذج هي أساسية فعلاً،
but let's look at how different teams perform.
لكن لنلقي نظرة على كيف تعمل الفرق المختلفة.
So the average for most people is around 20 inches;
إذاً فمتوسط معظم الناس هو حوالي 20 بوصة،
business schools students, about half of that;
طلاب إدارة الأعمال، حوالي نصف ذلك،
lawyers, a little better, but not much better than that,
المحامون، أفضل قليلاً، لكن ليس أفضل كثير عن ذلك،
kindergarteners, better than most adults.
تلاميذ رياض الأطفال، أفضل من معظم البالغين.
Who does the very best?
من هو أفضل الفاعلين؟
Architects and engineers, thankfully.
المهندسون والمعماريون، بحمد الله.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Thirty-nine inches is the tallest structure I've seen.
أطول الهياكل التي رأيتها بلغ 39 بوصة.
And why is it? Because they understand triangles
ولماذا هذا؟ لأنهم يفهمون المثلثات
and self-reinforcing geometrical patterns
والأنماط الهندسية التي تعيد ضبط نفسها
are the key to building
التي هي مفتاح بناء
stable structures.
هياكل مستقرة.
So CEOs, a little bit better than average,
لذا فالمدراء التنفيذيون، أفضل قليلاً عن المتوسط.
but here's where it gets interesting.
لكن هنا حيث يصير الأمر مثيراً.
If you put you put an executive admin. on the team,
إذا وضعت مديراً تنفيذياً. على رأس الفريق،
they get significantly better.
يتحسن أداؤهم بصورة ملحوظة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's incredible. You know, you look around, you go, "Oh, that team's going to win."
إنه مذهل. كما تعلمون، تنظرون في الجوار، وتقولون،" أوه، ذلك الفريق سيفوز."
You can just tell beforehand. And why is that?
يمكننا قول ذلك مسبقاً. ولم يحدث ذلك؟
Because they have special skills
لأن لديهم مهارات خاصة
of facilitation.
للتسيير.
They manage the process, they understand the process.
إنهم ينظمون العملية، ويفهمون العملية.
And any team who manages
وأي فريق يقوم بالتنظيم
and pays close attention to work
ويولي إهتمام شديد إلى العمل
will significantly improve the team's performance.
سيتحسن بشدة من أداءالفريق.
Specialized skills and facilitation skills
المهارات المتخصصة ومهارات التسيير،
are the combination that leads to strong success.
والتركيبة التي تقود إلى نجاح ساحق.
If you have 10 teams that typically perform,
إذا كان لديك 10 فرق تعمل تتنافس،
you'll get maybe six or so that have standing structures.
فأنت ستحصل على ربما ستة أو شئ كهذا من الهياكل المنتصبة.
And I tried something interesting.
وقد حاولت شيئاً مثيراً.
I thought, let's up the ante, once.
فكرت، لأفعلها بطريقة مختلفة.
So I offered a 10,000 dollar prize of software to the winning team.
لذا فقد عرضت جائزة قدرها 10،000 دولار من البرمجيات للفريق الفائز.
So what do you think happened to these design students?
إذاً ما الذي تعتقدون أنه حدث لتصاميم الطلاب هذه؟
What was the result?
ماذا كانت النتيجة؟
Here's what happened:
ها هو ما حدث.
Not one team had a standing structure.
لم ينجح حتى فريق واحد في إيقاف الهيكل.
If anyone had built, say, a one inch structure,
إذا بنى أي شخص ، لنقل، هيكل بطول بوصة واحدة،
they would have taken home the prize.
لكان بمستطاعه أخذ الجائزة معه.
So, isn't that interesting? That high stakes
إذاً، أليس ذلك مثيراً بأن الرهانات العالية
have a strong impact.
لديها تأثير قوي.
We did the exercise again with the same students.
قمنا بالتمرين مجدداً مع نفس الطلاب.
What do you think happened then?
ماذا تظنون الذي حدث عندئذ؟
So now they understand the value of prototyping.
إذاً الآن فهموا قيمة النموذج الأولي.
So the same team went from being the very worst
لذا فنفس الفريق تقدم من كونه الأسوأ
to being among the very best.
ليصبح ضمن أفضل الفرق.
They produced the tallest structures in the least amount of time.
لقد صنعوا أطول الهياكل في آخر الزمن المتاح.
So there's deep lessons for us
إذاً فهناك درساً بليغاً لنا
about the nature of incentives and success.
حول طبيعة الحوافز والنجاح.
So, you might ask: Why would anyone
إذاً، ربما تسألوا: لماذا يقضي
actually spend time writing a marshmallow challenge?
أي شخص الزمن في كتابة منافسة حلوى المارش مالو؟
And the reason is, I help create
والسبب هو، أنا أساعد في إنشاء
digital tools and processes
معدات رقمية وعمليات
to help teams build cars and video games
لمساعدة الفرق في بناء السيارات وألعاب الفيديو
and visual effects.
ومؤثرات مرئية.
And what the marshmallow challenge does
وما تفعله منافسة المارش مالو
is it helps them identify the hidden assumptions.
هي أنها تساعدهم في التعرف على الإفتراضات الخفية.
Because, frankly,
لأنه، بكل صراحة،
every project has its own marshmallow, doesn't it?
لكل مشروع المارش مالو خاصته، أليس كذلك.
The challenge provides a shared experience,
التحدي يقدم تجربة مشتركة،
a common language,
لغة مشتركة،
a common stance to build the right prototype.
موقف مشترك لنباء النموذج الصحيح.
And so, this is the value of the experience,
ولذا، هذه هي قيمة التجربة،
of this so simple exercise.
لهذا التمرين البسيط.
And those of you who are interested
ولأؤلئك الراغبين منكم،
may want to go to MarshmallowChallenge.com.
ربما يرغبون في زيارة marshmallowchallenge.com
It's a blog that you can look at
إنها مدونة يمكنكم النظر فيها
how to build the marshmallows.
لكيفية بناء مارش مالو.
There's step-by-step instructions on this.
وهناك تعليمات خطوة وبخطوة حول هذا.
There are crazy examples from around the world
وهناك نماذج مجنونة من كل أنحاء العالم
of how people tweak and adjust the system.
لكيفية ضبط الناس للنظام.
There's world records that are on this as well.
هناك أيضاً رقم قياسي عالمياً .
And the fundamental lesson, I believe,
والدرس الأساسي، كما أعتقد،
is that design truly is
هو أن التصميم حقيقة هو
a contact sport.
رياضة تواصل.
It demands that we bring all of our senses to the task,
إنه يتطلب منا تكريس كل إنتباهنا إلى المهمة،
and that we apply the very best of our thinking,
وأننا نطبق أفضل مافي تفكيرنا،
our feeling and our doing
مشاعرنا وفعلنا
to the challenge that we have at hand.
إلى التحدي الذي لدينا في أيدينا.
And sometimes, a little prototype of this experience
وبعض الأحيان، بناء نموذج أولي صغير لهذه التجربة
is all that it takes to turn us
هو كل ما يأخذه ليقلب حالنا
from an "uh-oh" moment to a "ta-da" moment.
من لحظة " أو-ها" إلى لحظة "تاداا".
And that can make a big difference.
ويمكن لذلك إحداث تغيير كبير.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)